Guide to the Records of the A/P/A Voices A COVID-19 Public Memory Project TAM.837
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Williams, Kai Naima, 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_79
  Kai Naima Williams was born and raised in New York City and identifies as multi-racial -- Japanese, Black American, and Jewish. Williams is a storyteller, published author, poet, and performer. She is the granddaughter of interviewer Tomie Arai and the great-granddaughter of activist Yuri Kochiyama.
- Wong, Alice, 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_80
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Rochelle Kwan on January 14, 2021. In this interview, Alice Wong talks about her experience as an Asian American woman with disabilities during the COVID-19 pandemic. During a time when people with disabilities were continued to be seen as disposable and Asian Americans were experiencing high rates of racist violence, her identity as an Asian American woman with disabilities placed her at the intersection of ableism, racism, and xenophobia. She reflects on the bittersweet transition to virtual gatherings from home, which forced many people to think about accessibility and workplace flexibility for the first time, despite longtime efforts to advocate for these things from the disability community. Wong discusses her and her community's history of online socializing and activism pre-pandemic; the erasure of these longtime efforts; and her hopes for the rest of the world to carry and adapt these lessons beyond the pandemic to ensure greater accessibility for all.
  Alice Wong is a disability activist, media maker, and consultant. For Wong, accessibility promotes connection and community, thereby fostering safety and care. She is the Founder and Director of the Disability Visibility Project, created in 2014, which is an online community dedicated to creating, sharing, and amplifying disability media and culture. Wong is the editor of Disability Visibility: First-Person Stories from the Twenty-First Century (Vintage Books, 2020), an anthology of essays by people with disabilities, and hosts the Disability Visibility Project podcast.
- Wong, Cheryl Wing-Zi, 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_81
  Materials include "Musings from Chinatown: Peri-Pandemic Notes on Resilience," a bilingual English and Chinese digital publication featuring contributions from Chinatown community members on how to stay resilient and how to remember the stories of Chinatowns. This publication was produced by Cheryl Wing-Zi Wong as part of the Calgary Chinatown artist residency commissioned by The City of Calgary's public art program in partnership with The New Gallery. This project is also supported by The Laundromat Project through the Creative Action Fund.
- Wong, Kristina, 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_82
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Preeti Sharma on July 7, 2021. A large majority of the interview focuses on Kristina Wong's experience as the founder of Auntie Sewing Squad, a group she says formed only because the government failed to properly provide masks for its people. Wong goes over some of the difficulties the group faced early on to produce masks when the demand for face coverings was overwhelming and sourcing materials was a struggle. Later in the conversation, Wong explains a shift in the Squad's priorities from hospitals to communities of color that did not have the same access to masks. While there were many other mask making groups who wanted to avoid politics, the Auntie Sewing Squad did not shy away. To them, mask making was inherently a political act. While Wong warmly shares her feelings of genuine love and community that developed out of the Squad, she does state she does not want the group to last forever and explains her reasons for not wanting to turn Auntie Sewing Squad into a non-profit.
  Kristina Wong is a third-generation Chinese American performance artist and Los Angeles, CA council member. Wong was raised in San Francisco, CA and as of 2020, she resides in Los Angeles' Koreatown. Wong had just started performing Kristina Wong for Public Office when the lockdowns started in California, but no longer able to perform, she decided to start Auntie Sewing Squad, a national group of volunteers who have been making masks for those in need during the COVID-19 pandemic. Inspired by her experience, Wong created a new performance called Kristina Wong Sweatshop Overlord. The New York Theater Workshop was streaming the performance from October 25, 2021 to December 14, 2021.
- W.O.W. Project, circa 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_77
  The W.O.W. Project is a female, queer, and trans-led community initiative using art and activism to grow and protect New York City Chinatown's creative culture.
  Materials include a copy of "Love Letters to Chinatown," which is a collection of love letters, poems, paintings, and essays dedicated to Chinatown.
- Xiong, Khaty, 2022; TW_TAM_837_ER_83
  Materials include a transcript from an oral history interview conducted by Tomie Arai on March 30, 2022. A photograph of Khaty Xiong's mother is also included.
  Xiong begins the interview talking about her work as a poet writing primarily about her experience dealing with deep loss. She describes herself as a "poet living in Ohio trying to make sense of the pandemic, writing a book about grief" and trying to build a space about grieving publicly, as New York University's Spring 2022 Artist in Residence. Setting up the installation in New York City was her first time traveling since the lockdown. Xiong talks in detail about the isolation and loneliness she felt while sheltering in place for two years; and how the quarantine and her loss of connection with community and family has impacted her life deeply. Xiong reflects on the reasons she became a poet and why she writes about grief, which is tied directly to her family's history and wartime experiences in Laos. As a way to deal with the anxiety she struggles with about her Hmong identity, she believes writing about hard things and writing poetry, while naming the process of grieving, is what empowers her.
  In the second part of the interview, Xiong shares a family photograph of her mother who is dressed in traditional Hmong clothing. She talks candidly about her mother's death, which was the impetus for the installation, "The Grief Garden," at NYU. Xiong describes the installation as a space for visitors to mourn privately as well as publicly, through the act of sharing handwritten stories about people they have lost on templates provided in the installation and adding them to the garden. She talks about her writing practice and the challenges she has faced as a Hmong poet. The interview ends with a discussion about memorials, memorialized spaces, and the mural "In the Future, Our Asian Community is Safe" by Jess X Snow, which touched Xiong and has given her hope.
  Khaty Xiong was born to Hmong refugees from Laos. She is the author of Poor Anima (Apogee Press, 2015), which is the first full-length collection of poetry published by a Hmong American woman in the United States. Xiong's work has been featured in The New York Times and How Do I Begin?: A Hmong American Literary Anthology (Heyday, 2011), as well as on the Poetry Society of America's website. Xiong was the Spring 2022 Artist-in-Residence at the A/P/A Institute at New York University.
- Yakupitiyage, Thanushka, 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_84
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Amita Manghnani on July 23, 2021. In this conversation Thanushka Yakupitiyage reflects on the events of March 2020 and the first weeks of the pandemic; the changes she witnessed in her Brooklyn neighborhood; and connects it to the news she was hearing from Southeast Asia, where her parents live and where she grew up. As a DJ, climate activist, and migrant rights organizer, Yakupitiyage talks about the challenges this time posed to her political and artistic work -- when people were prohibited from gathering together in physical spaces. She explores the questions: how do political organizers and cultural workers fulfill their goals? How does one organize and mobilize communities locally and globally? How can a DJ continue to create spaces of joy and connection?
  Yakupitiyage also analyzes the intersection between climate justice work, the existing inequities exposed by the COVID-19 pandemic, and forced migrations around the world. She speaks about her own experience as an immigrant to the U.S., the challenges in being so far away from her elderly parents who live in Asia, and vaccine inequity. Since Yakupitiyage is immunocompromised and has been a caretaker for an infant during this time, she has had a heightened sense of wanting to be careful during the pandemic. She speaks about the ways shifting gatherings to an online space has affected her, her sense of community, and the ways in which she responds emotionally to isolation during this time.
  Yakupitiyage comments on the rise of anti-Asian violence and highlights the ways South Asians have been left out of the conversation. She also addresses white performativity during the Black Lives Matter protests during the summer of 2020. She ends the interview speaking about her hopes for a different kind of future, and the ways in which community and relationships might form more intentionally.
  Thanushka Yakupitiyage is a Sri Lankan-born and Thailand raised activist; a cultural organizer; and DJ under the artist moniker "Ushka." She deejays from the perspective of a dancer, blending a wide range of club music from soca to dancehall, hip hop to South Asian rhythms, Baltimore/Jersey club to baile funk, vogue cuts to kuduro, azonto to Afrobeats and more. When she is not crafting dancefloor spaces, she's a political and cultural organizer.
  Yakupitiyage has performed across the United States, Mexico, and Canada—including at institutions such as the Brooklyn Museum, MoMA PS1, the American Museum of Natural History, and the Rubin Museum. She released mixtapes on Discwoman and The Fader; produced a sound piece for artist Mel Chin's installation at the Queens Museum; and played on the online music platform Boiler Room. She was NYU's Asian/Pacific/American Institute's 2018-2019 Artist-in-Residence and was selected to be one of fifty-two artists to produce new work for The Shed Open Call in 2019.
  Ushka collaborates with a wide range of DJs and producers including DJ Rupture, Tygapaw, Papi Juice, Uproot Andy, Riobamba, and Juliana Huxtable. For several years, Ushka has thrown a Queer and Trans People of Color (QTPOC) and immigrant-centered global club party with DJ Beto called iBomba.
- Yu, Betty, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_85
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Tomie Arai on October 22, 2020. Photographs, artwork, and videos related to Betty Yu's interactive project "Intimate/Distant: Family Roots + the Pandemic" are also included.
  In this interview, Yu talks extensively about her project, "Intimate/Distant," an interactive web-based documentary project that tells her family's immigrant stories through video, photographs, mixed media collages, and archival materials. The COVID-19 lockdown and the ways it has impacted her parent's relationship is at the center of these stories. The short video vignettes provide a portal into her family's journey, beginning with the COVID-19 global pandemic and going back to the early days of Chinese exclusion in 1882.
  Betty Yu is a multimedia artist, photographer, filmmaker, educator, and activist. She was born and raised in New York City to Chinese immigrant parents. Yu integrates documentary film, new media platforms, and community-infused approaches into her artistic practice; and has close to 20 years of community, media justice, and labor organizing experience. In 2015, along with ManSee Kong and Tomie Arai, Yu co-founded the Chinatown Art Brigade, a cultural collective using art to advance anti-gentrification organizing. As of 2020, she works as an adjunct assistant professor teaching new media, film theory, art and video production at various colleges in New York City, including The New School, John Jay College, Pratt Institute, Marymount Manhattan College, and Hunter College.
- Zaatari, Zeina, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_86
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Loubna Qutami on October 19, 2020. In the interview, Zeina Zaatari begins by speaking about her personal experience as both the director of the Arab-American Cultural Center and as a mother since the beginning of the pandemic; and the challenges of homeschooling and working from home. She then speaks about the Center, which is the only one of its kind nationwide, and the ways the pandemic has affected its programs. Zaatari also posits important opportunities for reflection and creative ways to continue student and community engagement despite new challenges. Zaatari speaks to the methodological process by which the center assesses the needs and interests of the students; and how it develops programs and initiatives that collectively engage and respond to pressing needs. Zaatari also speaks about how the pandemic has been felt in University life, how it poses potential permanent change to higher-education, and how it has affected the everyday lives of students at all levels. Placing these reflections into the broader political, racial, and economic context of the U.S. right now, Zaatari explores how the center has and continues to create values and practices that meaningfully reflect student/community understandings of justice and wellness.
  Dr. Zeina Zaatari is an Arab feminist scholar, organizer, and Director of the Arab-American Cultural Center at the University of Illinois, Chicago. Zaatari's organizing and research has largely focused on international feminist movements; and on women's rights and issues in the Middle East and North Africa, particularly Lebanon.
- Zen, Kate, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_87
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Minju Bae on September 29, 2020. In her interview, Kate Zen discusses the beginning of the pandemic; and how it affected her work and members of Red Canary Song. Speaking to uneven structural conditions for workers and tenants in Queens, Zen discusses the nature and impact of anti-Asian violence. She shares the story of Red Canary Song's founding and the collective's mutual aid work at the beginning of the pandemic. She also reflects on her concerns about migrant laborers; the U.S. and China trade war; and policing and urban development in New York City.
  Kate Zen is a sex worker rights activist; co-founder of Red Canary Song, a grassroots organization composed of Asian and migrant sex workers, as well as massage workers, who organize transnationally; and the Executive Director of the New York State Assembly Asian Pacific American Task Force.
- Zhang, Alex, 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_88
  Materials include a transcript and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Mi Hyun Yoon on March 16, 2021. In his interview, Alex Zhang speaks about his transition to a new job in the midst of the pandemic; his continuing to work remotely and having never met his coworkers in person; and what his job as a software engineer for an insurance company entails. Zhang also discusses being asked by his company to speak on a panel about anti-Asian racism and how his neighborhood in Hell's Kitchen has changed since the pandemic.
  The transcript and video files of this oral history interview can be accessed in the NYU Special Collections reading room only once permission has been obtained from Alex Zhang.
  Alex Zhang is a software engineer for the insurance company Haven Life. He identifies as Chinese American and lives and works in New York City.
- Zhou, XY, circa 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_89
  XY Zhou studied at New York University Gallatin School of Individualized Study and concentrated in art and culture, with a strong interest in writing. Zhou was raised in California's Bay Area and as the daughter of immigrant parents, she has always retained a strong tie to her cultural heritage. As a first-year student during the pandemic, she used art and writing to cope with the state of the world.
  Materials include two zines, "A Comparative Study of Two Chinese American Women" and "The Mystery of 7th Street"; artwork; and an essay titled "What the Pandemic Reveals About America's Cult of Productivity."